原视频名：Can SpaceX Catch a Starship Super Heavy (Like Falcon 9)
原作者名：NASASpaceflight
视频来源：youtu.be/OYvWYp0--bQ
原视频发布日期：20241010
字幕翻译：旋火
SpaceX has Falcon 9 booster landings down to a science
SpaceX将猎鹰9号助推器的着陆技术发挥到了极致
but we're really quick to declare that they've hit the bullseye
但是在火箭着陆在无人船上或返回着陆场时
when they land on the drone ship or back at the LZ
我们可以很快地宣布他们命中靶心
but how accurate are the landings actually?
但着陆的精度究竟有多高
And can we look at Falcon 9 landings
而我们能否通过观察猎鹰9号的着陆情况
and make any interesting estimates about how a Super Heavy Booster might land.
来对超重助推器的着陆方式做出有趣的估计
I'm John Galloway with NSF.
我是NASASpaceflight的John Galloway
And we've done an awful lot of analysis
我们做了大量分析
to try and figure out if the SpaceX landings are accurate enough
试图找出SpaceX的着陆是否足够准确
for the upcoming catch attempt of the Super Heavy Booster as part of the Starship program.
能使筷子回收成功
If you went back 10 years
如果你回到10年前
and you said yeah so here's what we're going to do.
你说我们要这么做
We're going to build a huge crane system
通过建造一个巨大的起重机系统
that's going to catch the booster by these little teeny tiny catch targets
使用这些小小的抓取设备来捕获助推器
and trust us it'll work.
同时相信这之中的成功几率
I think 10 years ago people would have thought you were insane.
我觉得10年前的人们会认为你疯了
But nowadays we've got rockets landing on barges that are pixels in the middle of the ocean.
但现在 我们已经让火箭降落在大海中央 和像素一样小的驳船上
So I'm not kidding.
所以我不是在开玩笑
It's amazing that SpaceX can so reliably get the Falcon 9 booster onto the drone ship or the landing zone.
SpaceX能如此可靠地将猎鹰9号助推器送上无人船或着陆区 实在令人惊叹
Of course it's super impressive to see happen every single time.
当然 每一次的成功都会给人留下深刻印象
I mean, Bingo right in the center.
我是说 好 就落在中间
Thanks Jack.
谢谢Jack的主持
And I think putting that rocket on that pixel in the middle of the ocean is a darn impressive feat.
我觉得把火箭放到海中央的像素点上 是个了不起的壮举
But is it actually a bullseye?
但它真的是命中了靶心吗
Now SpaceX has done this well over 300 times.
SpaceX已经回收了300多次火箭
The vast majority of which have been successful.
其中的绝大多数都取得了成功
So here's what we did.
那么我们是这么做的
We looked at video of over a hundred of the most recent Falcon 9 booster landing attempts
我们观看了最近一百多次猎鹰9号助推器着陆尝试的视频
to see if we could divine any accuracy numbers for them.
看看能不能猜测出精确度的数据
I mean how close close to the middle of the bullseye are they actually.
我是指 它们离靶心有多近
And once we got those numbers here's what we did.
一旦我们得到了这些数据 我们就要这么做
We put it in between the chopsticks.
我们把它放在筷子中间
And we tried to see what's the possibility that they can put that booster in between the chopsticks.
我们试着看看他们把助推器放在筷子中间的可能性有多大
Now up front there's a lot of qualitative analysis here that we tried to quantify as best we could
那么前面有很多定性分析 我们会尽量量化
but we were limited.
但我们的能力有限
We don't have actual statistics from SpaceX on exactly how far off center the booster is
我们没有SpaceX的实际数据 来说明助推器到底偏离中心多远
but we came up with a pretty good proxy for it.
但我们想出了一个很好的替代方案
And not all the booster landings were actually useful.
并不是所有的助推器着陆都是有用的
I mean some of them look like this.
我是指 有些看起来像这样
You can see the sides pretty well and there's about where the booster is, right?
你可以很清楚地看到回收船边缘 还有助推器的位置 对吧
But a lot of them end up looking like this.
但很多情况下是这样的
Can't really make any inferences from that.
我们无法从中得出任何推论
But in the end we found 84 Falcon 9 booster landing videos
但最终我们找到了84个猎鹰9号助推器的着陆视频
that we thought were useful enough to get some data about how accurately they actually landed these things.
我们认为这些视频足够有用 可以用来了解火箭着陆的精确度
Now I know a lot of you are already down in the comments
那么我知道你们很多人已经在评论了
like not a few minutes into the video already telling me why this is wrong.
只是看了几分钟视频就告诉我为什么这是错的
We're going to talk about that
我们(等下)会讨论这个问题
but there's still some really interesting engineering challenges that we can get to from the data that we collected.
但我们还是能从收集到的数据中发现一些有趣的工程挑战
Just bear with me don't make me reply to your comment.
只是忍耐一下不要迫使我回复你的评论
You didn't get to the end of the video, did you?
你还没看完视频 对吧
Now again we're looking at videos but here's what we did.
那么我们再次观看视频 但我们是这样做的
You got a booster and it's on a drone ship.
助推器着陆到无人船上
You want to make sure that you're consistently using comparable camera angles
你要确保使用的相机角度一致
and luckily we found that on most of the drone ships the camera angles were pretty reused.
而幸运的是 我们发现大部分无人船的相机角度都是差不多的
They were pretty consistent on where the camera was bolted to a railing or mounted or whatever.
相机固定在栏杆上 也可能是固定在其他地方 其角度都非常一致
We also had to throw out a lot where we just couldn't see what was going on.
我们也不得不丢掉很多看不清的镜头
I mean this is too blurry. I can't give you anything. I would just be guessing.
我是指 这太模糊了 不能得到任何信息 只能猜测
这里有一个助推器立在甲板上
But if you get a nice clear video, here's the plan.
但如果你能看到清晰的视频 计划是这样的
We take the sides of the drone ships.
我们从无人船的两侧下手
There's a side. There's another side.
分别有两边
Okay there are railings there and they're nice straight lines
栏杆是笔直的线条
and we can sort of compare those to each other so that's good.
然后我们可以把它们相互比较一下 这样就好了
We then wait until the booster lands and sort of settles, right?
得先等到助推器着陆并稳定下来 对吧
Now we need to do it right after the booster lands.
那么 我们需要在助推器着陆后立即进行
We can't wait until it gets all the way back to port
我们不能一直等到助推器返回到港口
cuz sometimes they tend to move around in rough Seas.
因为有时恶劣的海况会导致助推器在船上移动
But we'll draw a line about where the center of the booster is
但我们要在助推器的中心位置画一条线
and then it just comes down to ratios.
然后就看(其在船上的)比例了
Imagine that the entire width from railing to railing is 100
设想 从一侧栏杆到另一侧 整个宽度是100
how many percent are on this side and how many percent end up on this side.
两侧的百分比有多少
And that gives us sort of a centering number like 50 would be right in the middle.
比如50就在中间
Just because you get into okay measuring the booster
这只是测量助推器位置(的方法)
what's the focal length of the camera? Is it curved at all? Etc, etc.
那相机的焦距又是多少 画面又有多少畸变 等等
and let's just stay away from that.
这些问题我们就不讨论了
So for the 84 landings where we could actually see the railings
那么 对于这84个我们可以看到栏杆的着陆视频
and get a good line on where the middle of the booster was
同时还能把助推器中线画好的情况
we put that into a table.
我们将其放入一个表格
It's sort of a distribution curve, right?
这差不多是个分布曲线 对吧
There in the middle you can see the normal distribution assuming that it was all sort of there.
在中间 假定所有的东西都在那里 你可以看到正态分布
You can actually see some outliers maybe on the side.
实际上 你可以在边上看到一些异常值
Interestingly it seems like they trended a little bit more to the left
有趣的是 它们的趋势似乎更偏左一些
but we didn't go in and try to control for camera angles
但我们并没有去控制相机的角度
like oh this camera always has the launch site behind you
比如这个相机总是把发射场放在身后
sort of facing away and the booster is coming over your head as you land.
朝着远离发射场的方向 而着陆时 助推器会从头顶飞过
Stay away from that.
不考虑这些问题
Again the important thing is how close to each railing it is and the percentage thereof.
同样 重要的是它与每排栏杆的距离和比例
And you can see it does follow pretty much a curve
你可以看到 它确实遵循了一条曲线的趋势
and once we've got the curve we can get percentages.
而一旦我们有了曲线 就能得到百分比
Now the percentages here are where the middle of the booster ended up.
那么这里的百分比就是助推器中间的位置
Remember we're just drawing a straight line down the middle of the booster
记住 我们只是在助推器中间画了一条直线
and you can see they're pretty darn accurate.
你可以看到它们非常精确
68% of the landings that we analyzed ended up within this circle.
我们分析的68%的着陆点都在这个圆圈内
That's almost the center of the drone ship.
这几乎就是无人船的中心
95% of the landings we analyzed ended up within this circle.
我们分析的95%的着陆都在这个圆圈内
Still on the drone ship.
还是在无人船上
And if you get all the way out here, 99.7% of the landings occur within this circle.
如果你一直划到这儿 99.7%的着陆都在这个圈内
You can start to see why their booster landings on drone ships and back at the LZ are so accurate.
这就是为什么助推器在无人船上和陆上着陆场(后简称LZ)的着陆如此准确了
Quick note we didn't put any LZ landings in the analysis
说明一下 我们没有将LZ的情况纳入分析范围
because the camera angles tended to be a lot more variable.
因为LZ相机的拍摄角度往往变化很大
I mean they have a ton of land around the LZ
我是指LZ周围有大量土地
and they can sort of put cameras wherever
这样他们就可以把相机放在任何地方
versus on the drone ship
而在无人船上
you only have a certain number of railings that you can actually clamp those cameras to.
只有一定数量的栏杆可以安装相机
还有就是 谁关了灯
Is there some difference between RTLS and drone ship landings?
返场着陆和无人船着陆有什么不同吗
Not in this video.
本视频不会提及这个问题
In all the landings we looked at, we had to exclude about 34 of them.
在所有我们查看的着陆视频中 不得不排除其中34个
But it did end us up with a good sample size.
但最终我们得到了一个很好的样本量
84 landings and we weren't really trying to get rid of outliers.
也就是84次着陆 我们并没有试图剔除其中的异常值
Again we know that in the past boosters have completely missed the drone ship
我们也知道 过去助推器曾完全错过无人船
B1059在这里
享受生活
but we were looking at the most recent landings
但我们关注的是近期的着陆情况
So for the Falcon 9 booster, SpaceX is hitting that target very consistently.
因此 对于猎鹰9号助推器来说 SpaceX的回收命中率很高
No surprise there if you watch any of our streams.
如果你看过我们的直播 就不会感到惊讶了
And we get into assumption mode.
那么我们进入假设模式
Can we take the accuracy of the Falcon 9 landings and apply them to Super Heavy.
我们能否将猎鹰9号着陆的精度应用到超重助推器上
Clearly they are way different size rockets.
很明显 它们的火箭尺寸完全不同
But for the sake of our analysis
但为了我们的分析
because this is fun to think through
因为这样考虑很有趣
let's assume that SpaceX can get the big booster landings about as accurate as the small booster landings.
让我们假设SpaceX的大型助推器的着陆精度与小型助推器的相当
Falcon 9's not small.
(虽然说)猎鹰9号并不小
All right remember how big the drone ship is.
好吧 请记住无人船有多大
Let's take the drone ship and apply it to the closed chopsticks.
让我们把无人船应用到闭合的筷子上
You can see the chopsticks are a little bit smaller than the drone ship.
你会发现筷子比无人船小一点
But you can see when the chopsticks are closed they're just over 9 meters wide.
但是当筷子合拢时 其宽度刚刚超过9米
Well that's where they have to be to catch the booster, right.
对了 这个宽度就是助推器的宽度 这样才能捕获
And that's actually a lot smaller than the catchable area of the drone ship.
这比无人船的可捕获区域要小得多
When landing on the drone ship, you just have to get all four landing legs somewhere in that entire ball court.
在无人船上着陆时 四条着陆腿只需要放在平台上的某个地方就行
Aha, you might say.
啊哈 你可能会说
But the chopsticks don't have to be all the way closed when the booster enters the chopsticks.
但是 当助推器进入筷子(所包围的区域)时 筷子并不一定要完全合拢
Hold up we've seen this with the slap testing.
等一下 在拍击测试中我们已经发现了这一点
They actually have the chopsticks in an open position.
筷子实际上是张开的
And then they rapidly close them and then sort of make contact with the side of the tank.
然后迅速合拢 并与储罐侧面接触
Slap. We called it slap testing.
拍击 我们称之为拍击测试
So as the chopsticks are there waiting for the booster
所以当筷子在那里等待助推器时
they don't have to be like this.
它们不一定要闭合
They can actually open up a little bit.
可以张开一点
So that's going to increase what I'm going to call the catchable area on the chopsticks.
这样就能增加筷子的可捕获面积
And you have a little bit of leeway in here as well.
而且这里也有一点余地
Because the chopsticks can move.
因为筷子是可以(左右)移动的
We're going to talk more about this later.
我们稍后会详细讨论这个问题
But since the chopsticks are expected to be a little bit open whenever the booster bottom enters them
但是 因为在助推器底部进入筷子时 筷子会张开一点
and then close as the booster gets down to landing
然后在助推器着陆时合拢
here's what it might be.
情况可能是这样的
Now we've gauged this based on some of the slap testing and pantomime testing that we've seen occur, right,
那么我们是根据一些拍击测试和静默测试得出的结论 对吧
where they raise the chopsticks all the way up and they open them to a certain amount and then close them.
静默测试的时候 筷子升到最高 之后张开到一定程度再合上
This is not exact
这并不确切
更有可能是一个下限 这些测试使用的角度并不相同
but from a various different way of calculating them from various different camera angles, it's roughly 30°.
但从不同的相机角度计算 大概是30°
I mean if you do cosine math. it's like maybe 29° or 31°. We're just going to roll with that.
我是指 如果你做余弦计算 大概是29度或31度 我们就这么定了
I don't need somebody in the comments well actually it's 28.8.
我不需要有人在评论里说 实际上是28.8度
I mean we're making some big assumptions for this video.
我是指 我们为这个视频做了一些大的假设(所以不需要在意细节问题)
But still SpaceX has to solve these problems if they're ever going to have a chance of catching the booster.
但SpaceX必须解决这些问题 他们才有机会抓住助推器
So let's roughly say it's about 30° on each side from Center
所以我们可以粗略地说 每一边与中心偏离大约30°
which is a total of 60° roughly.
也就是大约60°
That's going to end up looking like this. There you go.
最终结果会是这样的
That's a lot more catchable area that they can hit.
筷子可捕获区域就更多了
Even though the chopsticks can be this open when the booster enters them
即使助推器进入筷子时 筷子可以张得这么开
they have to basically catch the booster by the ears.
筷子还是得抓住助推器的耳朵
Not really. There's these little pins that stick out of the side on the top of the booster, right?
其实不是耳朵 助推器顶部的侧面伸出了一些小插销 对吧
So you can't just say hooray the booster made it between the chopsticks.
所以你不能说助推器到达筷子中间就完事了
In between the time, the bottom of the booster enters the chopsticks
在捕获前 助推器的底部进入筷子(中间的区域)
and the pins past the catching area of the chopsticks, you've got to close those chopsticks.
在插销通过筷子的可捕获区域时 你得把筷子合上
But remember these are all percentages.
但要记住 这些都是百分比
It's like a 60 70% chance the center of the booster ends up here.
助推器的中心在这里的概率是60%到70%
But when you add in the booster's diameter
但如果加上助推器的直径
that ends up looking like this.
就会变成这样
Sort of decreases your margins a little bit.
这样一来 你的余量就会减少一点
And in that time you've got to get those chopsticks closed
这时候你得把筷子合上
such that both of the pins sticking out either side of the booster are caught.
这样 从助推器两侧伸出的两个插销都会被卡住
So understanding all that, we're going to sort of describe the catchable area with this orange shade.
了解了这些 我们就可以用橙色阴影来表现可捕获区域了
Maybe the booster could be a little bit further away from the tower.
也许助推器可以离塔架远一点
Maybe the booster could be closer to the tower.
也许助推器可以离塔架近一些
The chopsticks could be a little bit this way.
筷子可以往这边一点
筷子可以往那边一点
But you haven't hit the chopsticks which is a good start.
但只要还没碰到筷子就是个好的开始
Now again we're basing this orange area by the size of the catch rails
那么 我们再次根据捕获轨道的尺寸来确定这个橙色区域
that the pins are supposed to engage or be caught by.
而捕获轨道是让插销卡住的地方
It doesn't necessarily mean that the tower or the chopsticks
这并不一定意味着塔架或筷子
could take the force of a landing booster way out here on the end.
可以承受着陆时助推器在其末端产生的力
If it come in too close to the tower
如果它离塔架太近
it doesn't mean that you haven't impacted the tower
并不意味着你没有撞击塔架
and then corrected your position by the time you got to the chopsticks.
以及在之后要撞到筷子的时候修正了位置
But again let's forge ahead.
但我们还是要继续前进
So the booster hasn't hit the chopsticks but the pins need to be caught by the rails.
因此 助推器没有撞到筷子 但插销需要被轨道卡住
So from this slap testing
所以从这次拍击测试来看
it looks like they can in fact close the chopsticks fast enough to get them under the pins
他们实际上能以足够快的速度合拢筷子 使其位于筷子插销下方
while maintaining a larger possible catch area for the bottom of the booster to enter.
同时为助推器底部保持更大的可捕获区域
But here we run into another problem that Falcon 9 on the drone ship does not have.
但在这里 我们遇到了无人船上的猎鹰9号所没有的另一个问题
You don't have pins all the way around the top of the booster.
助推器顶部没有很多插销
You just have two, one on either side.
只有两个 一边一个
On the drone ship you can rotate however you want.
在无人船上 你可以随意旋转
It doesn't matter where the landing legs are as long as all four of them are on the ship.
只要四条腿都在船上 摆放的角度怎样并不重要
For the pins, the area that those pins have to touch down is way smaller than the surface of the drone ship.
对于插销来说 捕获轨道的面积远远小于无人船的面积
And here the roll of the booster becomes ridiculously important.
这样 助推器的滚转变得非常重要
Check this out.
看看这个
As the Super Heavy Booster rolls, the pins get further away from the rails.
随着超重助推器的滚转 插销会离轨道越来越远
And in fact if you're this far out of roll alignment, you miss.
事实上 如果你的滚转偏离轨道这么远 你就会错过
This is only based on rough visual estimates
这只是粗略的目测
but the pins stick out from the side of the booster only about 0.6 to 0.7 meters.
但插销从助推器侧面伸出的距离只有0.6到0.7米左右
And those pin, cylinders themselves take up part of that.
而这个距离还包括了插销圆柱体本身的一部分
So all in all given the size of the pins and the size of the ears
所以总的来说 考虑到插销或者说耳朵的尺寸
it only gives us about 12° of roll buffer if you will.
只能提供大约12°的滚转冗余度
In each direction from center, for a total of 24°.
从中心开始算起每个方向是12° 加起来总共24°
Now how accurately can SpaceX control the roll during these landing?
那么SpaceX在这些着陆过程中能多精确地控制滚转呢
Not really easy to see by analyzing drone ship footage unfortunately.
遗憾的是 通过分析无人船的画面并不容易看出来
Assuming your roll is within the margins
假设你的滚转在误差范围内
you've got the chopsticks closing together as the booster comes down.
助推器降落时 筷子已经合拢
Well how far are you from each chopstick.
那么每根筷子离助推器有多远
If you're right here in the middle and the chopsticks are moving at the same speed
如果助推器在中间 筷子以同样的速度移动
you impact the booster on both sides at the same time.
就会同时撞击助推器的两边
That's probably good.
这可能是好事
But what happens if you impact over here.
但如果撞击的位置在这里
You get into a situation where one chopstick has made contact before the other one has.
就会出现一根筷子比另一根筷子先接触的情况
Exactly where the booster is in that catchable area
助推器在可捕获区域的确切位置
changes how the chopsticks need to move in order to catch it.
改变了筷子的移动方式
Well you say why don't the chopsticks just push the booster into the right position.
好吧 你说为什么筷子不把助推器推到正确的位置呢
Now you've uncovered another problem
现在你又发现了一个问题
exactly where each chopstick makes contact with the booster body.
每根筷子与助推器本体接触的确切位置(的问题)
What happens if you're a little off center and one chopstick makes contact before the other.
如果你稍微偏离中心 一根筷子比另一根筷子先接触 那会发生什么呢
Pardon my plush booster. It's not to scale and I didn't have time to paint it.
请原谅我的毛绒助推器 它不符合比例 我也没时间给它上色
Didn't have to paint it.
没必要上色
But check this out.
但请看这个
If one chopstick makes contact before the other.
如果一根筷子先于另一根筷子接触
I don't know if you can see that.
我不知道你能不能看出来
Maybe we can do it in slow motion.
也许我们可以用慢动作来做
It can actually impart a rotation to the booster.
它实际上会给助推器带来旋转
The booster has mass, right?
助推器是有质量的 对吧
And the center of mass of the booster is going to be somewhere.
而助推器的质心会在某个地方
And it's sort of like where you can balance it.
就像是你可以平衡它的地方
There's the center of mass.
那里就是质心
But on the actual booster, it's got engines in the bottom
但实际的助推器底部有发动机
which moves the center of mass this way.
质心就会向下移动(因为发动机比较重)
So for the purposes of my model
所以对于我的模型的模拟来说
I've got to make contact here in the center of mass of the actual model
我必须在实际模型的质心这里进行接触
but if I hit it in the center of mass
但如果我撞击它的质心
I don't know if you're going to be able to see this.
我不知道你是否能看到这一点
You sort of push the entire thing over.
你差不多能把整个物体推动
You don't impart a rotation. You just move the whole thing.
你不会产生旋转 你只是移动了整个物体
But if you make contact above the center of mass or heaven help, you below the center of mass
但如果你在质心上方或下方进行接触
you get that rotation versus just pushing the whole thing sideways.
就会产生旋转 而不是把整个东西推向一边
Well why is this important?
为什么这很重要
Well one way to possibly mitigate any rotation imparted to the body of the booster
有一种方法可以减轻带给助推器本体的旋转
is to try and make contact close to the center of mass.
就是接触的位置尽量靠近质心
Now this may all be moot.
那么这一切可能都没有意义了
Here I don't have the force of the chopsticks
在这里 我不知道筷子的推力有多大
and I also don't know the inertia of the booster.
而我也不知道助推器的惯性
There's so many variables in here. All you could really do is just guesstimate.
这里的变量太多了你能做的只是猜测
They also might be able to tune the motion of each chopstick individually.
他们也许还能单独调整每根筷子的运动
It's not just start closing and hope the booster is in the middle.
这不仅仅是在助推器处在中间时(才)开始合拢
Maybe they can actually slow one down a little bit
也许他们真的可以把其中一根筷子的速度放慢一点
so that they still make contact at the same time.
使之同时接触
That's all going to come down to the telemetry
这一切都要看遥测数据
that's being shared in real time between the booster coming in for a landing or I guess I catch
助推器着陆时 实时共享的遥测数据
and the control systems that are telling the chopsticks yo it's time to close.
要传给(地面)控制系统 确定筷子夹持的时机
Here's how to do it.
具体方法是这样的
It'll be really interesting to see how this works out
这将是一个非常有趣的过程
but I bet you SpaceX has thought it through.
但我敢打赌 SpaceX已经考虑周全了
Now another thing about these massive amounts of energy that are being moved
那么还有一点 关于这移动中的巨大能量
when the chopsticks and the rocket are in this huge dynamic system.
也就是筷子和火箭处于这个巨大的动态系统中时
What happens if you slap it a little too hard and the chopstick bounces off?
如果你拍得太用力 筷子弹开了会怎么样
We've seen some mitigation for that.
我们已经看到了一些缓解措施
In fact I was referring to them as the steel newtons or catch cushions
事实上 我称之为钢牛顿或捕获垫
or whatever you want to call them if you watch the daily videos.
或者随便你怎么称呼它们 如果你每天都看视频的话
But we saw them install all of these bumpers along the area
但我们看到他们安装了这些保险杠
where the chopsticks is seemingly going to make contact with the booster.
处在筷子似乎会接触到助推器的地方
We can only guesstimate the exact operation of these
我们只能猜测它们的具体作用
but it looks like they're crumple zones almost.
但看起来像是缓冲区
So potentially the slap pads can absorb some of the force
所以这些拍击垫可能会吸收一些力
and make it more of a thud instead of a boing.
从而让它发出砰的一声而不是啵的一声
Not technical terms.
当然这不是专业术语
And that hopefully helps the chopsticks keep and maintain contact with the enemy
希望这能帮助筷子与敌人保持接触
or I guess the booster, which isn't the enemy here.
或者我猜是助推器 在这里助推器并不是敌人
Well it is the enemy if they don't catch it.
如果筷子抓不住助推器 它就是敌人
All right but what about vertical motion?
好吧 那垂直方向的运动呢
If you look at these detailed photos of the catch rails.
如果你看看这些捕获轨道的细节照片
The rails raise up and they have these dampers on them. Sort of this big hydraulic system.
轨道升起 上面有阻尼器 有点像大型的液压系统
And you can see that is also going to help absorb some of the force.
你可以看到这也有助于吸收一些力
You really don't want to have a picture-perfect catch
你真的不希望发生一次看上去完美的捕获
but have a little bit too much vertical momentum and then bounce off the chopsticks.
但因为垂直方向的动量有点大 导致其之后从筷子上弹起来
I think it's more likely that you rip the chopsticks off of the tower
我认为(过大的加速度)更有可能把筷子从塔上扯下来
but trying to mitigate and sort of damp out that vertical force is probably why they have these systems installed.
但他们安装这些系统的原因 可能是想减轻和抑制垂直方向的力
Now hydraulics seem rapidly reusable.
那么 液压系统似乎可以快速重复使用
Crush core, bumper crumple zones. Maybe not. Maybe they're springy.
压缩核心 保险杠溃缩区 这些装置也许就不是 也许可以回弹
Maybe they're just trying to get the first catch down by any means possible.
也许首次捕获就不管重复使用的事情了
Rapid reusability will come.
快速可重复使用(最终)会到来的
And as usual after we recorded this video there was late breaking news.
和往常一样 在我们录制完这段视频后 又有突发新闻
https://spacenews.com/nasa-really-looking-forward-to-next-starship-test-flight/
In a meeting that was publicly live streamed
在一次公开直播的会议上
SpaceX's Bill Gerstenmaier said that
SpaceX的比尔·杰斯滕迈尔说
the flight for booster landing happened with half a centimeter accuracy in the ocean.
助推器着陆溅落在海洋中的精度只有半厘米
Here he is.
他是这样说的
我们在海洋中的着陆精度达到了半厘米
所以我们觉得返回发射塔的可能性不小
Now if he truly meant half a centimeter that's less than a fifth of an inch.
那么如果他说的是半厘米 那就是不到0.2英寸
It's certainly possible that the that's correct but I can say this.
这当然有可能是对的 但我可以这么说
The Falcon 9 landings that we analyzed did not land with that sort of accuracy consistently
我们分析过的猎鹰9号的着陆 并没有持续保持这种精度
unless it was the drone ship that was consistently meters out of position.
除非是无人船持续偏离位置数米
Of course he did also say just sort of jokingly that
当然 他也开玩笑地说
they're either going to catch it or they're going to take out the tower.
他们要么抓住它 要么摧毁塔架
But there's one way to find out. We'll see what happens.
但只有一个办法能找出答案 我们拭目以待
So let's hit all this in a whirlwind.
那么简单来概括下吧
If it's reasonable assume that SpaceX guidance and navigation systems, GNC,
如果假设SpaceX的导航 制导与控制系统(GNC)
can get the Super Heavy Booster about as close to the target center as the Falcon 9's can
能让超重助推器像猎鹰9号一样接近目标中心的话
they've got a pretty darn good chance of getting it inside the chopsticks.
超重助推器落入筷子内部区域的概率就很高
But that's only the beginning of the things that have to go right for this to work.
但这仅仅是个开始
They have to make sure that both sides of the chopstick maintain contact with the booster.
他们必须确保筷子的两面都与助推器保持接触
They have to make sure that
他们必须确保
the booster doesn't get any tilt or rotation that's imparted by being slapped by the chopsticks.
助推器不会因为被筷子拍打而产生倾斜或旋转
They have to make sure the roll of the booster is close enough
他们必须确保助推器的滚转(偏差)足够接近
to get those pins above the rails so they can both engage.
使插销位于导轨上方 这样才能同时接合
It has to hit the catch rails with just enough force
助推器必须以恰好的力量撞击捕获轨道
so that it stays down but it doesn't rip the rails off or rip the chopsticks off the tower
这样才能保持向下的姿态 但又不会把轨道扯断或把筷子从塔架上扯下来
or make the carriage become disconnected from the rails that it rides on.
或者与轨道分离
So those touchdown velocities are going to be important as well.
所以着陆速度也很重要
And if all these things go right, you might have a successful catch of the Super Heavy Booster.
如果所有这些事情都能顺利进行 你就能成功捕获超重助推器
I'm sure we'll get a lot of comments down below with the flaws in the analysis
我相信评论区会有很多人对分析中的缺陷提出意见
because hey honestly there are limitations.
因为实话说 分析是有不足之处
We're looking at video footage not laser measure dimensions for all the landings.
我们看到的是视频片段 而不是所有着陆点的激光测量尺寸
And the boosters are vastly different animals.
而且助推器也大不相同
But hey I hope you have a better understanding of all the things that SpaceX has to sort out
但我希望你能更好地理解SpaceX需要解决的所有问题
to make this whole let's catch a rocket thing work.
才能让火箭顺利捕获
If you learn something, let us know down below in the comments.
如果你学到了什么 请在下面的评论中告诉我们
If you think I'm way off base
如果你觉得我说得有问题
hey I've been on the internet for a long time
嘿 我已经是老网民了
you can tell me that too no hard feelings.
你也可以告诉我 我不会生气的
Just be polite about it.
礼貌点就行
Anyway you slice it.
不管怎么说
When SpaceX finally gives this wacky idea and attempt
当SpaceX最终对这个古怪的想法进行尝试时
I guarantee you it's going to be exciting to watch
我向你保证 这肯定看起来让人兴奋
and we'll be here to share it with you.
而我们将在这里与你分享
If you want to make sure you don't miss those streams
如果你想确保不错过这些直播
make sure you click the sub button or whatever the kids are doing these days.
请务必点击订阅按钮
For now I'm John Galloway for NSF.
至于现在 我是NASASpaceflight的John Galloway
We'll see you nerds later.
我们稍后再见